King. He didn't have the money to give back to the king. What did he say to the king?
Did the king get mad or did he have mercy on the man?
When do you hear the word mercy in church? We are asking God to forgive us and be kind to us.
The man found a friend who owed him money. The friend didn't have the money to give to the man.
What do the friends say to the man?
Did the man have mercy on his friend?
The king was mad when he heard the news, who was he mad at?
Our Father in Heaven is like the king.
He will forgive us if we forgive those who hurt us.
Who have you forgiven?
Let us attend.
Send is gospel. 12th-Fangir children is a protection of the anti-okian Orthodox.
Department of Christian Education in partnership with HMFAith Radio. You can download an
Illustrated copy of the Gospel story at antiochiant.org slash Christian Education.
are troubled. All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and
bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits. 1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5. The modern world
doesn't acknowledge, but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to see and to
to no reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen De Young
host this live Colin show,
focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening one and all
This is nothing other than the 35th episode of the Lord of Spirits podcast known in some circles as
Pad Father Priests and Spooks
My co-host father Stephen D'Young is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana and I'm father and your Stephen D'Amick in a Mayas, Pennsylvania
And if you're listening to us live you can call in at 855 AF radio. That's 855-237-2346
With your questions about our topic tonight
Montesca Trudy will be taking your calls and we're gonna get to those in the second part of our show
So tonight, in your favorite, inexplicably weird Bible study said in the context of trying
to understand ancient people in their world, we will be looking at what the scripture says
about the priesthood.
It's a topic that seems to come up mainly when people want to argue about church leadership
and who gets to do it, but it actually has a rather deep and profound theological basis
that has written into the very fabric of creation itself and especially into humanity.
And I'm sure that is a big surprise for longtime listeners of this podcast.
surprise. So to bring us into what the priesthood is and means and does, according to the Bible,
well here's another big surprise. We're heading back to Genesis. So let's start with Adam.
Father Stephen was Adam a priest? Yes. All right, here we go. So he started out holy,
then he went shadow and then he respected discipline. I've got to riff on the title a little of the
So.
Nice.
Yes.
But that actually made sense to a tiny portion of our audience.
So have them forever now.
Yeah.
The we're going to start out with a little bit of review because any episode could be someone's
first.
And true.
It's true.
Although we do recommend everybody, you don't have to do it tonight.
But go back and start from the very first episode.
We do recommend that.
Get some...
more and more ridiculous every time we say it because right now you'd have to go listen
to like 50 some hours of us.
What else do they have to do with their lives though?
I don't know.
The world must be people.
Kids.
That's right.
Well, thank you.
The first Shakespeare quote for the night.
But since we're talking about going to talk about Adam as a priest, we've got to go back
I was about to say review.
quickly, but come on. This is us. The identification and understanding of paradise as a temple.
And so we've talked about this before, I think in multiple episodes, but so the to do this
relatively quickly. The pattern that we see in Genesis 1 and 2, of course,
responds very closely to what we see in ancient Near Eastern temple construction and dedication
texts, which you would think would be really boring. You would think would be like, yeah,
so we found a good piece of land and here's the dimensions and here's the layout, right?
It's actually not, it usually involves gods like killing.
chaos monsters, Ed-like flinging their bodies to the ground and using the blood and bones
to build things.
So as we talked about that sort of chaos comp for the war with chaos element is kind of
inverted a little bit in genesis one, but it does still sort of follow that format.
that culminates in the these axiomaries.
texts and in the process as it would have played out ritually when a material temple was built,
the sort of final step of that was placing the image of the deity within the temple, and then
the ceremony which would open its nostrils, which would then allow the spirit to enter into it.
right and in to ellet and then that would be the
point at which the people could then interact with the God
ritually. And we've talked about how we see exactly that
reversed in Genesis 2 with Adam, where still at the end of
the process, Adam is made as the image of God. He's made and
that he's placed within the garden as a temple. Right. But
that Adam, as we said, that is inverted, he is to image God
in the
world and that idea of imaging as we've talked about before is not just a nominal idea, it's
not just a noun, but is a verbal idea that he actively images God.
Yeah, and one of the big differences between the way that Genesis presents this narrative
is that God himself places this image within his temple slash garden versus the pagan
stories where constructing a temple ultimately the image is being placed by the pagan worshipers.
Right. So yeah. Yeah. Which is a big, big important, very important discontinuity.
Right. Because they are using the temple of the rituals to act upon the God.
Right. To get the God to do what they want, to maintain a fellowship with the God. Right.
This is vice versa right Adam is great at sharing God's life and to continue
the work of God in creation as we've talked about. So we talked about expansion of Eden.
Right. And so, first three days of creation in Genesis 1, God is putting things in order. Right?
He's separating the light from the darkness, separating the sea in the sky, separating the dry land
from the waters, putting all those things in order. And then in days 4 through 6, he fills in the same
order those spaces.
that he set out put an order, he fills them with life, with living things.
And so the command that's given to Adam and then when humanity is divided into man and woman
that's given to them is to fill the earth and subdue it, to put the earth in order and to fill it
it with life. And so the intent was that they would exit out of Eden and bring Eden with them.
And as they did that, as they put things in order to fill it with life,
those parts of the world, those parts of the earth,
would be integrated into Eden.
So Eden would sort of expand.
Right?
There would be sort of annexed.
And when we're talking about Adam is priest,
this is important because that expansion was Adam's offering.
One of the primary
ways in which he was to put the world in order, right, was to take all of the things of creation
and offer them back to God in this sacrificial way, right, blessing and sanctifying them,
making them holy and thereby integrating them into paradise.
Yep.
And so that is sort of the offering function there.
Right. So it was not a question of he was going around.
He was supposed to go out of eating to find animals to sacrifice and then use their blood to
like claim that piece of ground. Right.
But that was that was the sense. So that kind of offering,
right, is far more like the Eucharist than like the offerings of the old covenant you might notice.
Right, because it's about incorporating rather than...
You know, bringing, as you said, rather than going, bringing in something from the outside,
it's about sort of incorporating what's there and offering that to God.
Right.
And why was that?
Well, that was because the sacrifices of the Torah in particular, but even the ones before
that were about cleansing and purification from sin and its effects, which didn't need
to happen yet.
Right.
It's not a thing.
But so if we want to give sort of the quick definition then of what a priest is,
starting with Adam, right, the priest represents God to the rest of two other humans and really
to the whole creation. Right, right, represents God to the creation in that, right, like Adam,
putting things in order, filling them with life, participating in the ongoing work of
God in the world.
I'll just say naming them as well, you know.
Right.
Yeah.
That is participating in the work of God in the world.
So the works of God are coming into the world through humanity.
He doesn't need humanity.
Right.
He chooses to do it through humanity.
And then the flip side is that he represents man, other humans, and really the whole creation
Back to God.
Right. Right. This incorporation, this lifting up in prayer, in worship, in inner sessions, in blessing,
right before God. Yeah. And even though this is not what we're going to super get into in this
particular episode, you know, when death and sin and so forth come in, that's why so much of this
stuff gets upended and distorted and destroyed is that the relationship of the creation to God,
God.
that Adam was supposed to be maintaining
that all gets broken as a result.
Right. Right.
Yeah. And so priesthood then is not like a job,
like a particular job, a particular profession.
It's not like a power position or
a, um, an author.
right? That's especially with Adam, right? Yeah, none of that stuff. I mean, those are all like socially
socially relative kinds of terms, right? You know, and that doesn't exist in Eden because it's just Adam,
right? And then you got Eve or whatever, but it's not. Yeah, yeah. There's no offices. There's no titles.
titles. Right, but it's a it's a way in which Adam is to interact with the world. Right.
away he is to interface with the world,
away with which he is supposed to see and interpret the world,
and the things in the world, right?
So he's too relate to the animals, the plants,
the other people as one who is offering them up to God
and who is representing God to them, right?
That's how he is to interact,
see the world and experience it.
That's what priesthood is.
Yeah, and really, yeah.
And I was going to say and even on the
way of sort of extending that language is to say also that he offers God to the world
and offers the world to God as part of it as well.
Right.
Yeah.
He is sort of a conduit, right, that runs in both directions.
Right.
And so this is because this is a way of relating to the world and a way of being in relationship
to God in the world.
Right. This is really an element of what we call human nature.
Right. It's built right into what it means to be human.
It's built into the creation itself.
Yeah. And we'll probably need to do an episode at some point where we just go
through some of these terms, but like a lot of the terms we've talked about,
we've talked about so many terms where like image that we review tonight,
where these things have really become sort of reified in our usage and in our
right? To the point that we'll even talk about like when we're talking about
Christology, we'll say Christ took a human nature. Right? Like human nature is a
thing, right? Like it's a human body, which it expressly is not at least in
the sense we usually think about bodies as material. There's another word we
overly, rayified.
But, and so nature is, and it's original use,
usage is a directness of being. It is a sort of and directness in a in a
teleological sense, meaning a purpose or an aim or a goal, right? So an acorn
has the nature of an oak tree, meaning that if it is planted and if all goes
well, right? And if it was if it is free to grow fully into its nature.
that is right the end of it, right? We'll be, we'll look like that, right? And so I believe it was
St. Basil the great, correct me if I'm wrong, and you know who said that that a human being is the
being whose end is God in a sense of tell us. That sounds super familiar, but I can't, yeah, they're
confirmed nor denied.
talking about, talking about, I'm sure you'd agree with it even if it was another father.
But the idea there being, right, that obviously and Christ being where we look for this,
Christ is where we look to see what humanity is supposed to look like and what God looks
like, that that is sort of the end, right?
if all went well that is what our humanity would
look like and one element of that, right?
One element of that is, meaning one element
of how are being as humans, how are human nature's directed,
is this idea of priesthood.
Yeah, I'm reminded a little bit
that teleological definition of,
it's not exactly the same thing,
but it's the same sort of idea that line from Saint Augustine,
which I don't know if he really said this,
or if this is a misattribution,
but you know, which I always love the way it gets rendered
in English, our hearts to lever restless B
until they find their rest.
in the, which is that same kind of idea that this is Christ is who and what, you know,
we're meant for, you know, and we're just not really, truly, fully human in every way
we can be until we're in Christ.
Right.
And so this is sort of built into our human nature.
And now, as we already mentioned, and this has to be a threat addressed if we're talking
about.
priesthood, that humanity, as we mentioned, gets separated into man and woman.
Right.
So, I think we've mentioned before, right, that when this happens, when humanity is divided
into man and woman, man and woman sort of major in one of those two tasks.
So man.
majors in the task of setting the world in order and women majors in the task of bringing
life into the world. And that second one is, you know, we can see in a pretty literal sense,
but is also true beyond that literal sense. Right. Right. But ideally, right, ideally, both are
participating with the other in the other's work, right?
So again, we can very literally see that for a woman to literally bring new life into the world, a man has to participate.
Right.
That's how the system works.
But also, for a man to set the world in order in a way which will then allow it to be filled with life.
Right, that requires the participation of woman.
This is part of the mystery of marriage
and the two becoming one flesh
is that these two can become perfectly reunited
in order to accomplish both tasks.
Right.
There are ways of bringing life into the world
that are pure chaos.
There's a bayou, not far from where I'm sitting right now.
That's a good example.
It is full of life.
Life that will kill you, if you go down there
at the wrong time, but life, not the last.
That is out of control, right?
Right.
And even destructive at times.
And also very tasty at times.
Yeah.
What properly said in order.
Yes.
By frying.
But,
Right?
But there's also obviously an ordering of the creation
that is anti-life.
Right?
These two are not opposed to each other by nature,
but they can
be if they don't each have the participation of the other.
Right.
I mean, it's a point of cooperation.
It's a point of which ordering becomes tyrannical, right?
I mean, you know, this is, right?
This is back to Leviathan and Behemoth, right?
Right.
Yeah.
Leviathan is sort of a chaotic life, so to speak, and Behemoth is a tyrannical order.
But yeah, you know, again, there's it's that old little Latin saying, you know, a
uses non-tolid oosom, right, which I'm sure I'm mispronouncing, but the idea that just
because there's an abuse of something does not negate its proper use.
Right.
And we actually see the place where this goes wrong in Genesis 3, where in the curse
that's put on the curse that's pronounced regarding the woman, it's usually, or at least
often translated into English.
Your desire will be for your husband, but he will reign over you.
Right. Right. Right. And that's what that saying is,
desire being sort of on the chaos and bringing life into the world side and
reigning or ruling or dominating being on the order side and both of them
now rather than cooperating together to create, right, in the world,
world are now opposed to each other, right, and committed to...
to dominate each other.
It's now a power dynamic, right?
Where each side is trying to dominate the other
rather than this cooperation.
And that is one of the results of Adam and Eve coming
to know evil.
Yeah.
Yep.
And so, and that rain language, right?
You may have noticed.
See, we've been talking about Adam SA.
priest, but there's also been a lot of setting in order, naming the animals, which as we
talked about, you see in in Hittite iconography, you see their kings naming animals as
a way of saying they're the king. So there's also this sort of king idea mixed in there.
And we have to remember that until a point we're going to talk about in a little bit in
act to, priest and king are still together right now. Right? These aren't separate ideas.
right everywhere in the world pretty much you have priest kings at this point
yeah in history and Adam really is one too right and there's this idea as
well of especially since in many cases you're talking about really early
civilizations where you know the whole kingdom so to speak is basically just a
massive family you know there's there's and and this is it's interesting like
this gets reflected in fact in length.
So even the English word king, and yes, I know, you know, etymology does not determine meaning, but...
But, you know, at some point in the history of the English language, the word king, which was cuneing in old English,
it comes from the word cune, which becomes our modern word kin, and it means almost exactly the same thing then that it does now.
does now. And so the idea is that the king is the kin person. You know, he's the one who's bringing
the kin together and putting them, as you said, in order, which, I mean, I was just kind
of a side comment. It always makes me sort of roll my eyes when I see sometimes people complaining
about scripture language about the kingdom of God and saying, no, no, it should be about
the kingdom of God. I'm like, that's literally where this word has its origin. It really is
about kin. But I mean, it's about putting the kin in order.
I think you're the only one who sees people doing that.
I am probably okay
But no, it's out there.
You take care of them for us.
I will.
Oh, I am.
I am.
But yeah, it's definitely a thing,
like this idea of kingdom, not kingdom.
Like, oh, anyway.
We really not people do not want to be enlightened
by my etymological wisdom.
I don't know why that is.
But yeah, they sound like tiresome people,
I mean, to be sure.
So maybe I'm glad I haven't met them.
This is the same world where people say amen and a women.
I'm like, that's,
Oh yeah, amen has nothing
do with with mailness at all. Yeah. Any head entry, run wild. So I'm gonna put things in order.
But this we should also say that, you know, this while obviously
It shouldn't be hard to convince anyone that the proper relationship of men and women.
women has fallen away into a kind of struggle for power. I don't think it'd be
hard to convince anyone of that at least in today's day and age. It's also true
that that participation is still there as the ideal. Right. Right. As the ideal.
And this is why you can see this in certain places. This happens in the
scriptures, right? Isaiah's wife is called the prophetess, right? Because she
participate.
in his prophetic right ministry and activity.
And in the Orthodox Church, if a priest is a Presbyterre,
we have a, and you're married, your wife is a Presbyterre,
which you could literally translate priestess.
Right.
That doesn't mean she is doing the same things I'm doing, right?
But, and even, and even the operation is there.
And say, and even in the period where we had married
bishops early early early on, they were called up
or sometimes occasionally the bishop's mom was called a Piscopa.
There's this participation in his role as a bishop.
Right, so that is still held out as the goal and the ideal.
And of course, the conceiving and birthing of children is related to this as sort of a sign and
and a symbol in the positive sense of that.
Right?
That it's not limited to that.
But that is a marker that is a clear visible and material sort of marker of what all of marriage, all of matrimonies, should be about.
So, relatedly, what we see as we go through the rest of the book of Genesis, as the patriarchal narratives roll out.
Um
And are we gonna have to think of something else to call those?
I don't know.
Is that gonna be bad?
I mean, they are the patriarchs.
I mean, what can you say?
Like, this is the word.
I don't know.
But I don't think we have a lot of people deeply concerned with political progress.
Just bring it to this podcast.
Just bringing sure.
But if you are out there, we're glad to have you.
Yes.
said your angry emails to father and her dammit curse.
So what we see and prominent examples of these, this would be like Abraham, Isaac, Jacob,
Job, right?
The patriarchs, a forenamed, is we see the fathers as in not the father of a nuclear family.
We need to pause here a second.
Okay.
I know that nuclear families ingrained into all of our brains as what a family...
family is, right? And some folks even, this is gets mixed up in politics and stuff, and
they think the nuclear family is some kind of Christian ideal. The nuclear family did
not exist before industrialization.
Yeah, it was just not really even possible economically for a family to survive that way
in most cases. Right. Everybody thinks about little house in the prairie and whatever
but yeah, it's not man-woman children. It's it's man-woman uncle aunt
and cousins, grandma, grandpa, great grandma, great grandpa.
Which, I mean, a lot of people in the world still live that way.
Like, a lot of my wife's family who live in Lebanon,
they all live in the same building.
Right.
They're just all together.
And so it's worth reiterating, right?
Because, you know, when we talk about Abraham and his family,
we're not talking about Abraham, Sarah, Isaac, and maybe Ishmael.
Right?
We're talking about all of them plus
plus all of his servants, plus all of it, right, all the extended relatives.
So the social structures that we're going to be talking about these going forward.
So it's worth taking a little time here to lay this out, right?
We're coming to act two.
So the social structures at this point, you have these extended family units, right?
And you'll have several of those that are also related but more distantly that make up
a clan.
Right.
They'll generally be these large extended family units that have a common sort of ancestor,
maybe two or three generations back.
And that'll be a clan.
And then a group of clans, which generally that group of clans, which they will have
a story at least that they're all distantly related to each other by blood.
whether that's...
actually by blood or whether there was adoption as we've talked about it before, right?
And other people entering in is often not totally clear.
But those clans that will make up a tribal unit, right?
So like this is how Israel is going to be set up later.
And this is how Israel's neighbors are mostly set up.
Yeah.
I mean, when you look at, like almost any cult.
when you look at it like its mythology and the description of families and so forth.
Like that's the way that things are set up is a lot of those stories come out of these tribal periods
and there's always, you know, and there's always one man who's at the head of the whole thing
and it's related to at least half of them in a pretty demonstrable way, you know.
And then a lot of the authority flows from him to members of his family, you know.
Right. And this is going to be true in cities too.
Yeah, right cities you're gonna have
these extended family units and even clans and then the king of a city state is going
to be seen as sort of the father of the whole unit.
Right. Right. And so within these social structures, the fathers of the extended families,
right, sort of sort of the elder of each of those families, right, the patriarch of each
of those families. So Abraham, Isaac, Jacob, Job, they're the ones who are performing
the priestly functions. They are the ones we see going and
offering sacrifices. Right? They're the ones who we see offering not just other people,
but the elements of creation back to God and representing God to them. Right? So God is working
in the world through them to both to their families and to the world and they're coming back to
represent the world to God. So think about Abraham sort of bargaining with God over whether or not
that he does.
destroy Sodom and Gomorrah, right?
Interceding for Sodom and Gomorrah.
Right. And it's not this, again, it's not like a separate profession, like the butcher,
the baker, the candlestick maker, and the priest.
It's, this is his task as the head of the family.
Yes. Yes.
So priesthood and fatherhood in this sense are built together.
Anyone who's seen as a father is also seen as a priest, right?
including the king, so like Melchizedek, who's a priest.
king. Right? See the epithel episode we did about milk is an act. Yes, right? But he is the king.
He has seen as the father. Therefore, he's functioning as a priest. Right. And so these two things are
deeply connected. Right? This is what fatherhood is is priesthood. And what priesthood is is in a
sense fatherhood. Right. You can't separate those those two fully.
And so this is a part.
We're going to get into this more later because we decided to be super controversial this time.
But this is part of why, as we're already seeing, we have male priests.
Right? Because this is what fatherhood is.
And I don't think we're going to touch on this super directly later.
let's go ahead and do it now. Okay. As we talked about, we're saying now priesthood is particularly
related to fatherhood and to masculinity, that it sort of constitutes it. Right. And so why is that?
Right. Why is that? Well, if you study the Torah very much, and if you have in your brain,
as we don't always have, where if you have in mind that
to pay attention to men and women in the Torah.
What you'll find for example is that almost all
of the commandments and when you get to issues
like sexuality, all of the commandments
are directed to men and not women.
Right, which follows the general pattern
in the Old Testament particularly that you see where,
and even in the New Testament,
where the person who has the
the choice in a matter or the power or authority or whatever, those are the ones that God is talking to and usually putting limits on that person.
Right. Right. And it's not just limits. Right. Yeah. Right. But, but on the whole, right, the males of the human species are more physically powerful. Right.
just and physically dominant.
Right.
Which is why you get in society's all
over the world, far more commonly patriarchy than matriarchy. Right. And so it is male energy
in particular. It is that male energy to put things in order. Right. To subdue. Subdued
very quickly becomes dominate. Yeah. That's not what it's supposed to be. It's more like
cultivate, right? Build.
And so male energy has a particular need to be channeled in certain ways.
Right. And the way in which it can be channeled positively to result in theosis, to result in
becoming more like God. Right. As part of our human nature as it was meant to be, is priesthood.
Hmm, okay. So priesthood is part and parcel of masculinity because in this world
because it is what masculinity needs in this world
in order to find salvation.
Right?
And we could equal, well, I'm a man.
So I couldn't equally well talk about,
but I could also talk about that motherhood,
which is not limited to physical, biological motherhood,
but also includes spiritual motherhood.
just like priesthood includes spiritual.
fatherhood is what is needed for women to channel that feminine energy into producing life
instead of producing chaos.
So these, when people, part of the problem is that traditionally in our culture and in
sort of the purest and influenced Protestant culture of the US.
I'm not even specific.
talking about Protestant churches now. I'm just talking about American culture.
Right. As it's been influenced by Puritan Protestantism. The discussion tends to be about gender
roles and those roles are spoken of as being assigned. Right. Right. So it's seen as like,
this is what you are going to do. Right. That's because some authority has said so. And used to
to be that authority was going to...
God, this is what God says, said men are supposed to do and women are supposed to do.
And if you're disobedient, that's bad and you'll be punished.
Since most people now in American culture have gotten rid of the God part, it's just sort
of the culture has said it or Western structural structures.
Western tradition has said it.
And that of course is much more open to question, which is why we have a lot of the chaos we do.
Right.
So we need to think about this more like when...
Paul says everything is permissible to me, but not everything is beneficial.
Yeah, right.
Yeah, so it's not about who's allowed to do what it's really about what is it that's
actually going to bring a person to holiness.
Right.
How will each person find salvation?
Yeah.
And so as we're going to see as we keep going now, that doesn't mean that every male human
needs to become a priest, the way you and I are priests.
Right.
Oh lord.
All are called to priesthood in this priesthood.
Yes, to priesthood in various contexts.
Right.
And it's not that women aren't called to priesthood, but women are called to experience that by participating in the men's priesthood.
by being their wives, by being their mothers, by being their spiritual mothers.
Right. By being their daughters, right, in all of those ways. Right. So, all right, as we're
saying, this is a means of exercising authority, right, the authority that's been given
to Abraham Isaac Jacob Job, Melchizedek, right, in their various social units, that authority
can be used by them in a lot of different ways, right?
And...
Melchizedek is definitely an exception among ancient pagan priest kings, right?
He's not really a pagan, but you know what I mean, right?
And so this is a way of channeling, right and of directing that authority and utilizing it, right? And so we talked about how
priesthood then can be seen in terms of being this sort of
conduit right that that worship the worship of
the people, right, passes through them to God, prayer and worship with people passes through
them to God. And then it goes the other way. Right. God's grace, the works of God, the divine
energies, right? God working in the world passes through them to the people and to the creation.
Right. And I see. And I see. They don't get in the way. Yeah. Right. So that's where and this is
the problem. I'm sure some people hearing that to be like, well, that really gives a lot of
powers of the priest, right?
But I mean, again, anything can be abused.
And the way that in the ancient world that we see it abuse is that the priest king
sets himself up as a God king.
Right. You know that he, that instead of just being the person that the worship passes through to God,
he now expects God. He expects to be worshiped as a God.
and also instead of just
being the guy that the grace of the God passes through him to the people, like a lot of it sort of
stops with him. He's being charged up by the God. And he dominates the people. Yeah, yeah, which
is, you know, like this is this pagan model of priesthood, fatherhood, kingship, is exactly the
model that I think a lot of, you know, even well-meaning Christians react against because they see
this corrupt
version of priesthood, right? That it's about dominating people and about, you know, thinking
that you're holy and can dispense all graces and, you know, if I may say so, the key to
the storehouse of merit, that kind of thing, right? That's the kind of thing that people
reacting against, and it's precisely this, this is where that comes from, right? Now,
Man, you pagan God king priests are being very explicit about it.
You know, they're
they're saying, yes, I'm a God, worship me. But you know, and, and, and, you know, no Christian
worth is salt even a tiny little bit would ever say such a thing about himself. But, but that's
the way when people react against priesthood very negatively, the priesthood they're reacting
against is this kind of paganized version. Right. Because this isn't saying you need an intermediary
between you and God. This isn't saying you need another mediator other than Christ between you
in God, right? Because I
ideally, if he's doing it right, he virtually ceases to exist.
Right. He becomes sort of transparent.
This is dying to self, right? Yeah.
This is ego death. This is saying John the four runners saying he must
increased and I must decrease. Yeah. Right. This is the priest is the
one who connects people to God and God to people and then gets out of
away right? That's the ideal here not that he is imposing it.
In fact, if he's imposing himself in between and asserting himself in between by definition
like these pagan priests kings, he's doing it wrong, and he's usurping God's authority.
Yeah, that's the thing.
Which is bad.
Which is usurpation, right?
For the record, bad.
Yeah, right.
And I mean, and this is one of the primary evil things that you can do in Scripture is
the usurpation of God's authority, whether it's a pagan priest king doing it for himself,
or people.
worshiping a demon who's doing that, you know, taking the place of God by accepting worship.
Idolatry, right? Right. Right. And this, this shows,
high Jordan B Cooper, if you're listening. This shows why not only is iconography and the
veneration of icons in the church, not idolatry, it is literally the opposite of idolatry.
Hmm.
performing the imaging function of God.
The image of God is the opposite of idolatry.
Because idolatry is definitionally, right,
whether it be the pagan priest king,
who's seen as the embodiment of the God,
right, like the Pharaoh being the incarnate Horus,
right, or different gods at different stages,
in Egyptian history, or whether we're talking about
stone or wood and idle, right? That object or person is by definition this kind of intermediary
who comes between right. It's the body of a god.
It's the body of a god.
Right. Who receives instead. And who excurs the exercise authority instead. Whereas an icon.
Yeah. Well an icon, right? And St. John of Damascus reminds us again and again, right? Remember
the veneration, the honor.
passes through it, right, to the one depicted, right?
That's why the window to heaven language, right?
A lot of folks have really kind of been
trashing that language lately.
And I understand why, because the idea that like,
oh, you're looking into a window and seeing heaven, right?
But I don't think that was the original intent,
or I'm gonna give the benefit of the doubt
that that was not the original intent.
I'm hoping the original intent,
because this expresses something very true,
Is it?
they were referring to the icon as being transparent.
Right. Like glass. Yeah. And you know, to use, as you said, the conduit
language, idolatry is when the conduit gets sort of stopped up.
Yes. You know, then the worship stops there or the, the, the, you know,
divine power stops there and resides in that thing. You know,
That's the problem.
you know, that yeah, yeah, exactly, you know, it's like it's damned up so to speak.
Right. And, and, and this was sometimes seen as happening quite literally.
So there are in second temple literature examples of whether trying to explain
what's going on with golden calves, whether we're talking about the one in Exodus
or we're talking about the ones Jeroboam Son of Nebath set up, right?
That kind of thing where someone makes an idol of Yahweh that got of Israel.
Right? So kind of representation. A very common Jewish interpretation of what happened there and why it was wrong was because someone could come and say, well, okay, I mean, but they're trying to worship the God of Israel. They're doing it the wrong way.
Right? But they're sort of trying in a bad way to worship the God of Israel. Right? But the way they saw it happening is they argued that that demons would enter into those idols and the demons would sort of intercept the people.
what sort of intercept.
it, like intercept the worship, right? Like insert themselves in between and block the blessings,
right? To quote certain preachers, right? So that's what we're talking about, we're talking about
idolatry, we're talking about this instrumentalization, right? One way or the other or both ways,
right? So if it's a priest king, it's working both ways, right? Whether he's pagan, priest kings or
or God kings.
uh, he's, he's interposing in both ways between God and the people and between the people in God.
Within a physical idol that can't see or hear or talk, it's between the people in God.
Right. It's not even performing the other function at all. Right. Um, but uh, that then
repeat is the opposite of imaging. Right. When, when milk is a deck as a priest king,
served as a pre-skinned.
He was serving as an image of the God who created the universe to his people.
So David, when he was imaging God in the divine council with his human council, he's imaging.
He's not putting himself in between.
He's not demanding O'Peeces for himself instead of God.
That's the key, the key difference, and what makes them opposites.
Yeah, exactly, exactly.
All right, we are going to take a short break,
and we'll be back with your calls.
Call in, if you have questions about the priesthood,
that's what we're talking about tonight,
and we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Steven DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Are you curious about the Orthodox Christian faith?
Do you have questions about Orthodox Christianity that you can't trust strangers in internet
forums to answer?
Are you an Orthodox Christian looking for a reliable first place to send your interested friends?
Do you need help finding an Orthodox church near you?
My name is Father Paul Hodg.
by serving the Ant2.
and orthodox Christian archdiocese of North America.
My name is Father Joseph Lucas.
I serve in the orthodox church in America.
My name is Father Anthony Cook.
I serve in the Greek orthodox archdiocese of America.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
Chief Content Officer of Ancient Faith Ministries,
and a priest of the Antiochian Archdiocese.
And we're the orthodox intro team.
If you're looking for a first stop online
to get an introduction to the orthodox faith,
a place to get answers to questions.
from qualified Orthodox Christian clergy.
A place to send your friends
and not just toss them into the chaos of the Internet.
A place to get help finding an Orthodox parish
and get plugged into an actual Orthodox community
then point your web browser at orthroxintro.org.
Orthroxintro.org is a free service of ancient faith ministries
and made possible by our donors.
It's an Orthodox enramp to the Christian life.
Again, that's Orthodoxintro.org.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Welcome back. It's the second half of
of this evening's episode of the Lord of Spirits.
We're talking about the priesthood.
And just like you heard, the voice of Steve said,
you can give us a call if you have questions about that
at A55 AF radio.
Again, that's A552372346.
So we've laid out exactly what it means
that priesthood is kind of baked into the creation
and baked into humanity, and especially into fatherhood, right?
And we talked about how that contrasts with the
way that paganism distorted all of that. So now we're going to kind of move forward a little
bit chronologically in the scriptures and talk about the way that the priesthood begins to change
because of some things that happen, right? So let's talk about Moses. So what goes on with him,
father? A bunch of stuff. Some stuff. That's all that Exodus,
Yeah, good night.
It feels that Egyptian dude.
Yeah.
It is addition to that and related to priesthood.
So now that we're out of the book of Genesis,
we're coming into the book of Exodus,
what's gonna happen is that priesthood is going to get fractured.
That's what we're gonna be talking about in this act.
And the second half, we're gonna be sort of going through
and seeing how we talked about how before
Exodus in Genesis. There's not sort of a priesthood, right?
Like Abraham didn't go and find a priest when he wanted to offer a sacrifice. He just did it.
Yeah, he didn't get ordained by somebody. Right.
So but then there is this now going to be a priesthood obviously spoilers in the Old Testament
And that represents priesthood now being set.
separated off to a particular group and that actually begins with Moses himself, right?
And to understand that, we have to talk about one of the really weird,
well, this includes one of the really weird episodes in the book of Exodus.
There's more to it than that.
And a lot of what's going on in it is hidden behind euphemisms and de-ufamizing it slightly.
a little bit. Not completely, because family show and our lead in was just like a children's
gospel reading. So now I feel bad if I scarse someone for life by talking about this too
bluntly. But so we're pretty familiar with the first part of Exodus 4 where God has this
exchange with Moses, right, like at the burning.
and tells Moses to go back to Egypt.
And Moses is like nah.
Right.
That's a literal translation of the Hebrew.
Yeah.
Low.
So it gets to that.
Right.
It starts out with a lot of excuse making.
It starts out with me no talk good.
Right.
You know, I, I, I'm not going to get killed.
and is that there's somebody else you could pay
And finally, it's just sort of like I don't want to do it, right?
Right.
And God sort of gets in the text increasingly angry about this, right?
And remember the angel of the Lord has involved in this too, right?
This is one of the places where we see, and we mentioned this in our pre-Christmas series,
This is one of the places where you see the angel of the Lord and the bush and then
and also Yahweh talking from the bush,
where they're distinguished but yet identified.
And so there's this increasing sort of irritation with Moses.
Right, which I mean, like, let's just take a second here
and realize that here is Moses literally,
literally looking God in the face,
and he's standing there making excuses.
Yeah.
I, which I mean, you know, it's comfortable to think,
well, I would have done differently,
but I am not even 10% as holy as Moses.
So...
Probably not. I don't know.
Man, God wants me to give back the extra change I got at Walmart and I make excuses when
we're talking about it. Right, exactly.
Yeah.
And also, this is right when, like, you know, part of this is God showing Moses the signs
that he's about to be able to do. Like the thing with the staff and put his hand inside
his clothes, you know, like all this kind of stuff. Like, here's some miracles, Moses, and
still he's still like really do I have to yeah so
Yeah, may he intercede for us?
So and I have an icon of him staring at me right now, so I won't be too critical
right but
So
What God says is
Well, I'll send Aaron
Right to help you and in fact he says you know what?
God having known this was gonna happen said he's already on his way here, right? So why don't you just head out toward each other?
and he'll meet you on the way and the two of you can go to Egypt together. And Moses says,
okay, and then heads in the opposite direction. Right. And so he pulls a Jonah, although
yes, or should say that Jonah pulls a Moses, I don't know, but yeah. And so as he's heading
in the opposite direction, who should he run into? Not Aaron, because Aaron's coming for the other
direction but his wife, Zappora, Zappora.
So in this encounter we find out that the angel of the Lord is about to kill him.
Right. Kill Moses. Right. And so it's not just that he was making all the excuses.
It's not just that he was running in the other direction. But we now find out that Moses had not
circumcised himself and had not circumcised his son. Which again, this is basic, you know,
constitutive belonging to the
family of God, kind of like this is, you know, this is this is
utterly baseline stuff. Like you have to be circumcised if you're
going to be part of the covenant people. And you know, here is
Moses about to be the prophet of God to the people and he has not
even done this most basic thing for himself and his sons.
Right. This is like fighting out your bishop was never baptized.
Right. Right. Right. Right. And so,
So, Zappora is actually mad at Moses about this.
right because this could have left her a widow and potentially there could have been consequences for her son
and so when she shows up and again this is some of the stuff that's hidden beneath the euphemism
but she throws the results of her having circumcised their son at Moses and she takes the knife
Bye.
the knife that she used to do it and places it in the place where she would have to place
it to also circumcise Moses.
And says, uh, the name of the list is usually translated as you have become a bridegroom of
blood to me.
Right.
Meeting.
I married you.
I had this child with you and look at this misery.
right and wrath that you've potential
brought upon me. Right? So after this episode, right, is where we find out that it's going to be Aaron,
who is going to be the high priest. Aaron and his sons are going to have the priest that the now
existing priesthood. Right? So what's happening here is that the priesthood is being taken away from
Moses. He still has that kind of kingly leadership role.
But the priesthood has been taken away from him and isolated with Aaron and his sons as
opposed to Moses and his sons.
Because, you know, up to this point, him having this sort of patriarchal position, he would
have been the priest of the people or the prior priest.
Right.
The same way Abraham was.
Yeah.
Yeah, exactly.
He's now in the place of Abraham essentially.
Right.
And this is not just sort of a random punishment, right or an
arbitrary kind of punishment. This is related to the fact the specific his specific failing.
Right. His specific failing was as a father. Right. Because this is the thing that a father
is supposed to be doing. Right. He failed to be a priest for his own family. And if you can't be
a priest for your own family, then you can't be a priest for the broader community. Yep. Right.
say Paul's gonna make this point later on.
in the New Testament.
Is this where he's getting it, right?
You can't.
You can't hold up.
That's like, no.
That's later.
Sorry, that's the thing.
We'll talk about that more in the third.
Yeah, yes, sir.
But, right, so you can't do it on this larger scale
if you can't do it on this smaller scale, right?
And so it's given to Aaron.
And so here, the king and high priest are separated,
and they're going to remain separated
throughout the rest of, well, the person who's supposed
to be the king and the
the person who's supposed to be the high priest will remain separated throughout the rest of the Old Testament.
These will be two different things. Right.
And later on, as we move through the Old Testament, the line of the high priest is going to in various stages get sort of winnowed down.
Hmm right so it starts with Aaron and his son.
but it's not going to be like all of Aaron's descendants of the high-presley family.
There are going to be several important junctures.
The first of those is Phineas, who I know we've talked about before,
because I just like triggering people by talking about Phineas.
His name is actually an Egyptian name.
Egyptian name is Pinyas, which is one of the words for a Nubian.
It means the black skinned one.
Right. So his mother.
he's Aaron's grandson. His mother was from Putt, which is Southern Libya and she was an African woman.
And Phineas is the one who intercedes violently at the Book of Numbers at incident at Bailer Baal Payor.
This is chapter 24.
Yeah, a group of Moabite and Midianite women who are not just some random women looking for husbands
They are shrine
prostitutes seduce the number of Israelite men into participating in the rituals there at the high place
And this includes some of them even bringing some of these
Shrine prostitutes into the camp
and defiling the camp and finious intercedes with a speed
to put an end to that and then it is his descendants who then the family the
high priest will come down come from and then several centuries later in the
high priesthood is is winnowed down again to the family of Zadok the the faithful
high priest and so this will sort of continue in terms of who is going to be
high-pressed. So that's...
the high priest, right, but there's also just priests, right?
There's sort of the general priesthood, right?
You're you're you're run of the mill priests, not just the singular high priest, right?
And these are the people who are doing most of the things, right?
When you read the the rituals, right?
I mean, the high priest is involved at the day of atonement.
He has this special role.
There are a couple other places where he has a special role.
But the day-to-day stuff in the tabernacles being done by the priests.
Yes, others.
There's just one high priesthood of time, is that right?
Right.
Yeah.
So despite this happening pretty early on in Exodus,
from then until through the Exodus,
and even once they come out into the wilderness to Mount Sinai,
the people who are doing those sort of regular day-to-day
priestly functions are still the elders of the people,
the Presbyteres in Greek.
Right, the Presbyterian in Greek.
Who, as we mentioned before in those social units, each of these extended families,
right, that was in these clients, each of these clients, they had an elder, right, a Presbyter, a leader, and
The President tears of the 12 tribes, 70 or 72 of them, I tend to think 72 just because it's an even multiple of 12, but...
Hmm.
It could be either number.
Then we're sort of the the the elders of the people as a whole, right?
The Chris Bitterett as a whole and they were the ones who were still offering sacrifices for their
families
Right, they're still fulfilling that same function. The priesthood had not been taken away from them. The way it was taken away from Moses
yet
Right here.
So we see this play out in the episode with the golden calf in Exodus 32.
Right. Where they decide to try to use the techniques of idolatry to worship Yahweh.
Right. Right. So Moses is up on the mountain. He's gone too long. Right.
It's dark up there and scary. So they say, ah, he must have died up there.
here. Hey, Aaron, you know, here's all here's a bunch of
golden jewelry that we looted from the Egyptians on our way out. Make us, make us a God
to worship. So he makes what is probably an apis bull, an Egyptian style apis bull, and
Aaron points at it and says, here is Yahweh your God who brought you out of Egypt. And
more euphemisms, but the text in most English translation says something like they sat
out.
eat and then rose up to play. Yeah, which means that they engage in the pagan orgy. Right,
right. They had pagan sacrifices. They had a sacrificial feast and then an orgy. Yes.
That's what that is saying. It's not saying that they ate a light lunch and then played
a little bit of that.
The Royal Game of Er, perhaps?
Yes.
Yeah.
So.
And then of course, you know, we've seen this dramatized with Charlton Heston and everything right Moses comes back down and finds them
Inflate grante de l'Icto
and
Is quite upset right and is going to put a stop to this and he says who will stand with me and the people who stand with him are
The the heads of the clans from his own tribe the Levites
And so they then join with him to restore justice right in this situation which involves killing a whole lot of people
And the destruction of the golden calf and the punishment of Aaron and etc etc
And a plague
Yes, yeah, lots of bad, yeah, so
So they bring down upon themselves with this.
So it is at this point explicitly that the priesthood is taken away from the elders of the people and given to the Levites.
So not only the high priestly line, right, high priestly family is going to be there within one of the clans, but the priestly clans are going to be part of the tribe of Levites.
the rest of the Levites are going to have these.
and then we're going to have
a lot of
priestly roles, right, in
relationship to the other
tribes. Yeah, right. Yeah.
And so before we move on to the
next thing, we actually do have
someone calling. Okay. So, yeah,
in fact, he has the very best
possible name. So, Andrew, are you
there?
Are we connected with Andrew?
You can call us on the line.
time.
All right, well, I'm not hearing Andrew, but he's probably not even blonde.
Well, yeah.
So all right.
Well, so Andrew, are you there?
Speak to us.
I think we might have lost him.
Who did this to you?
All right.
Well, Andrew, if you're there, give us a call back and hopefully we'll get reconnected
and we can talk to you.
So, um, okay, well, all right, well, let's, uh, let's talk about the sons of
back to Andrew. Are you there now? Are you there now, Andrew?
I'm there now. Can you all hear me? Yes, we hear you. Welcome. Welcome to the
Lord of Spirits podcast. Andrew, what is your question or your comment with
that glorious name that you have? Yeah, my, my question kind of goes back to
what you were talking about earlier with the priesthood being the kind of
of the archetypes of God-
masculinity. I was just wondering what are some of the bigger challenges that you two face
and kind of manifesting that in a world where masculinity can be seen in negative light
in some cases a borderline pejorative?
Yeah, it's a good question. I mean, I've thought about this a lot, especially because, you know,
I'm not only a priest of the church, but I'm also a father of four children.
You know, and so I remember one of the things that my own spiritual father told me one time is he said that a
Priests ability to minister the grace for that comes from within his life at home
Right now. I mean, it's not making a you know the point that he was making was not to say like that there's some kind of
mystical force that makes that happen or whatever but rather that
you know exactly this point that that father Stephen said earlier which you know say Paul said which is you know if a man cannot be a priest within his own family then how can he offer that to the church right and I've experienced this myself you know it as a struggle and it's and it's always I think one of the big struggles that that fathers and husbands have is you know we get home we've worked hard and we just want to sit down and just chill out and you know please
please don't ask me to do anything, right?
Everybody feels that way at the end of a work day.
And yet the reality is that that man
is supposed to be leading his family
among other things in prayer.
And especially like if someone's in a ordained priest
who were like, look, I pray all the time
as part of my job, do I have to,
you know, you have the feeling, right?
It's his temptation.
But I've found that, you know,
it's one of the most beautiful things within a family
And it's not.
easy. It's really important to struggle in that direction, but it's true what my spiritual father
said that there is a grace that comes from within that that empowers the ministry in general.
Right? So if things are not in order at home, especially in terms of that man suffering and sacrificing
and leading his family and prayer, then he's not going to be able to do it well outside of the home.
right and you know you mentioned also as I said I have a lot of opinions about this.
You mentioned also this idea that masculinity has become almost kind of like a dirty word
in the modern age.
And I think part of it is because of the way that a lot of people have attempted to exercise
masculinity, which is exactly in this kind of paganized fashion where it's about dominating
people, right?
And the truth, I always tell people, it's so funny.
There is this whole sort of thing that people talk about online trying to kind of reassert,
to quote manliness, right?
And I've seen a lot of people talk about this who are not husbands or fathers and have never really
suffered or sacrificed in their lives. And I'm like, you know, it's okay to talk about this stuff,
but you really don't know what you're talking about because real masculinity is about sacrificing
oneself and becoming that conduit. And it's not always comfortable, not even usually comfortable,
Right, it is about sacrificing.
for the people that God has given to you.
And that's what makes a man a man.
Right, it's not about, you know, being dominating
or assertive or any of that kind of stuff.
It's really about being willing to sacrifice.
So that's my experience with that.
And another senior priest that told me something really good
was he said, you need to get control of yourself
and then that will
stabilize your family and your community.
Very, very wise words.
So I don't know, Father Steven,
do you have anything you wanted to add to any of that?
Well, I mean, being super rugged and brawny,
it just kind of comes naturally to me.
But, no.
No, Father Steven is not a small dude.
I'll just say that everybody.
But, part of the,
the part of the
the issue I think is that a lot of the stuff about like how do I be a man? How do I be masculine
that we have in the modern age? Like I understand why people feel that way, right?
Yeah. But a lot of the way it plays out is in sort of this really neurotic way of
I want other people to see me as a man, right? I want other people to look at me in a certain way
Right, and I need to try to figure out how to reshape my
or say the right things or grow the right beard or whatever so that people will see me that way as being
manly or being masculine. And coming off as sort of neurotic and insecure about your masculinity is
like the least manly thing in the world. So it's sort of this badly reflexive thing so that people don't
see you that way so that you get even more insecure, right? And like you get this like
Death struggle with your own ego.
Yeah.
And the problem is right there at the beginning
where you're wanting people to look at you and see you.
Right?
As we were talking about, this is about a large way
about transparency and about getting out of the way.
Right?
So you said what kind of obstacles do we face?
My biggest obstacle always has been
and I think always will be my own ego.
Right, my own sense of myself.
right, getting in the way because I kind of want to be in the way. I kind of don't want to get out of the way. Right?
Like, you know, you can performatively going around, go around acting like you don't care what people think, but that's a sure sign that you care what people think.
Right? Your ego can just trap you that way.
I think on a practical level, right?
One of the things about being a...
man that's been totally lost in our world. And I think this is in part because as we're
talking about the sort of idea of the nuclear family has replaced a lot of much better ideas,
like of the extended family and of the village and of the community. That for example,
one of the really masculine things you could do that falls into this priesthood example is
is provide for people.
And I-
don't mean by that, right?
You need to make a lot of money and provide,
you know, put designer shoes on your kids
and jewelry on your wife, right?
That's not what I mean.
What I mean is, for example, helping another man
in your community get a job,
giving him a job, being a mentor to a younger man,
teaching somebody a skill, right?
where it's not about you, it's about them.
and getting them connected to something, right?
Helping them grow into the man that they can be, right?
Rather than focusing on yourself, right?
And can I finish earlier with sacrificing yourself
for the community?
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, we need to get past the idea
that identity is about what separates me from everyone else.
Identity is
who I am in my family, who I am in my community, right?
That's who I am, right?
So I don't have an identity off by myself as an individual,
right? It's how I relate and how I interface
and doing that in this priestly way, right?
Is what takes care of that masculinity and manliness thing?
and manliness thing.
Does that make sense Andrew?
I know.
It does, yeah, all really great stuff and it's just, you know, I thought that you were
going along as that.
Even whether or not, like you said, there's kind of, there's priests in the church and
then there's kind of the general, everyone is called to the lowercase P priesthood that
like you said, offers God to the world of the world to God.
But I think part of that is in order to do that, you have to be in the world.
to interact with the world. And that's just just curious is to, you know, what your challenges
were and how you guys have been able to manifest that and struggle through that. Yep. Yep.
I would agree with Father Stephen that my biggest obstacle is his ego. No, it's my ego.
And I think that that's, I mean, I think it's true for all of us, right? The humility is the
the thing we're struggling towards.
My ego is bigger than his and wields a club.
So there we are. All right. Thank you very much, Andrew, for that call.
Yes. Thank you, Daniel, very much.
All right. All right.
Okay. Well, let's talk about the sons of Kora.
Yes. Yeah. So we want to talk about the sons of Kora in order to disambiguate something.
Right. And that's that where we've been talking about the restriction of the priesthood.
going to being reserved in the old
in the Sinai Covenant to this particular group of people,
there's been a lot of violence involved, right?
So one could almost say that they've sort of seized
the priesthood by violence, right?
If one wanted to take that read, right?
But we have an episode here in the Torah
where someone tries to sort of seize
the priesthood by violence, right?
Right.
Um, tissue.
that that's not what this is about. Right? That's not what this is about. That this is about
faithfulness and faithfulness. Right? And those who are faithfulness, you know, those who have
little, even what they have, is taken away. Right? Those who have been faithfulness, with a little
who's taken away from them and given to those who are faithful. And so that episode that sort of
of disambiguate this is in number 16.
It is a story of, as you mentioned,
Chakora's rebellion, Kora and a couple other clan heads within Levite's decide that Aaron
should be the one who gets to be the priest and his sons. It should be Kora and they
should be able to be high priest too.
And the way he expresses this in the text is rather literally
is not everyone in Israel holy, each and every one of us, are we not holy? And
therefore why should you be a priest? It's set yourself above the rest of us.
Right, that's verse three of number 16. Yeah, I will leave it to you if that sounds
like anyone you may know. Anyway. But so, Quora makes this argument. And what Quora
is really arguing, though, at the core is that God did not make Aaron the high
the air in his line.
right and then he set himself up as the high priest. God did not put Moses and Aaron in these positions, but they're just lying and saying that they put themselves in those positions.
And so this sort of it's not really a test to the sort of thing is set up where they're all going to gather with sensors and there's there's kind of a telegraphic of what's about to happen because they send messengers to all the people who are near the tents of Korra and the other rebels to kind of
to kind of...
back away slowly. Right. Right.
And then what happens is the ground ends up opening up and
uh, uh, Korra and his, uh, fellows go down alive into
sheel. They go down alive into Hades. Right.
And, uh, as someone said after a lecture I gave on Tuesday night
where I also talked about chorus rebellion.
day reverse Elijah by going down alive into shiel. But so it is not a question of sort
of the priesthood being something seized by violence. It isn't like becoming captain
of a Klingon ship where you assassinate the old captain and now you're in charge.
And that's the way things work on a Klingon vessel. So and you don't have to eat gaw though
either so that's not good. But, um, but that it's.
It's about this function of justice.
Remember justice is everything being in the right order.
This ordering function of the priesthood.
So the Levites, Phineas, they help restore order.
They perform that ordering function and that's why the priesthood is given to them.
Because they're acting as priests.
Right? And Korra is doing the opposite. Right?
he's doing the opposite of that, which is why he not only loses his
Levitical status but his life.
So he has some sons who survive and write some Psalms, but that's for another episode.
Right, the Psalms of the Son of Korah.
The Son of Korah.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, if you read, yeah, it's just as a note, you know, like if you guys,
if you read the Psalter, you'll sometimes see at the beginning, it'll say something like,
like, you know, for the chief musician or, you know, for the sons of
Korra.
And there it is. So like the sons of courier are like a chanting group basically
You know later on right as you said. Yeah. Yeah. It's 11 solms between
42 and 88 or 41 and 87 depending on whether you're using
The Hebrew or Greek numbering right
But so this creates the situation then
where we have the high-prease.
right, which is this particular family, Aaron's family, and then particularly
Phineas' branch, and then particularly Zedox branch, right? And then we have
priestly clans within the Levites, right, who the priests come from. So this is a
bigger structure surrounding that. And then we have the other Levites who are
sort of in supporting roles. We'll talk more about them later, right? Who are
doing sort of all the other tasks to assist, right, that are required.
this both the Levi man and the Levi women are doing some of those tasks right and so you can
picture this as sort of concentric circles right where you've got the inner circle would be
the high priesthood then the priesthood around that and then the tribe of Levi around that
Right, in these concentric circles.
Yeah.
And so...
One important note here, and this is related to when the high priesthood is established,
the high priesthood is established with when you read the Torah, it's described a couple
of times in great detail, particular investments, right, not just a particular role, but he presents
himself, he appears in a certain way, both before God and before the people.
this is command, I mean, you know, it should go without saying, but this is commanded by God.
God, like he's not like, oh, I have an idea.
I'll make my self look fantastic with super fancy vestments.
Yeah.
God says, no, this is what you're going to wear.
It's going to look like this.
I mean, there's a lot of very specific liturgical instructions
in the Old Testament.
Right.
Yeah, including the name of Yahweh, written on a plate
on the front of his head dress.
But this is because, right?
This is insane.
service of making him into once he puts these vestments on, he is now not Aaron or
Eleazar or Phineas or whoever, right? Once he has these vestments on, he is now the icon of
Yahweh the God of Israel, right? And he is to perform this imaging function, right? And so part of the
The vestments is reducing, minimizing, losing.
the individuality of the person, right? Part of that transparency. That serving is a conduit.
And interestingly, a part of that, right, is that the way in which these
vestments are described, when we compare this to other things in the ancient
Near East, they're described as the vest, in the same way as the vestments that were put on idols in pagan temples.
Hmm. The priest of those pagan temples.
would come and dress the idols and feed them and all of those things, right? And care for them.
Kathy Bates style. And
wow. And so
and so
Aaron is dressed the way they were to again this is going back to Adam, right? The tabernacle
is going to have...
not just the cherubim but also especially prominent in the temple, right, trees, fruit trees, right?
These are reconstructions of paradise. And so the high priest is then in there taking the place of
Adam, in paradise, right? As the image, the imager of God, right? And another part of those
those vacancies in the e-fod that sort of-
of breastplate. He's got the stones, the precious stones with the names of the 12 tribes. Because
when he goes and he comes before God, he's bringing the people before God with him. Right.
Right. This is the basic priestly function. Right. So the imaging is working both ways. Right. And
that's built into these vestments. Right. And there are other things that are inverted about this.
Right. We just mentioned not only did they dress the the
of the God, but they'd also come and feed the God. And we have the table with the showbread
often spelled with an E, but it's still pronounced showbread.
The shoebread? Yeah, you want to say shoebread, but that's not what it is. It's showbread.
It's really the bread of the presence in the original, right? And that bread is not brought there
by the priests to feed to the God of Israel, but that bread is there on this table in the Tabernacle
for the priests to eat during their service.
Yeah, and the table itself,
like actually I was just looking at this in Scripture recently,
like the table itself is covered in gold,
and I mean, it's really something.
It's not just some little buffet table.
And table. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah, it's really, really something.
Right, because this is God's table.
And He is feeding His priests,
so it's directly inverted.
Yeah. Right.
Yes, the host.
He feeds the priest, feeds Israel.
Right, exactly.
That the priests are there in persona Israel.
I don't know how you would work that out in Latin,
but you get the idea.
So, all right, well, before we move on to the next point,
we actually do have another caller.
So, Kavya, are you there?
Yes, I am.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Kavya, what's on your mind?
Thank you.
So, I actually have the reverse of Andrew's question
earlier about priesthood and gender.
So you talked about what can be done to sort of image priesthood in a masculine sense.
I'm thinking about the feminine sense as well.
So for those of us who are not literal mothers or nuns, what is spiritual motherhood?
Like what does it mean to bring life into the world?
Hmm, that's a good question.
Father Steve, I'm going to let you go first on this one.
Punt.
So, I'm not counting, I think that's...
I think you're putting your try to think of something, but I'll give you some time here.
Don't worry.
I'll cover for you.
All right.
I'm going to go make some coffee.
I'll be right back.
Right.
So, first of all, first of all, it's important that we talk about that participation, right?
That participation element, right?
So part of it is now, this is going to be more, like for example, an obvious example
is for some...
someone who is a literal mother, obviously parenting should not be each parent performing
different functions, right?
Like, they should be participating together.
But also this takes place in the community setting.
The same thing applies that I was saying in terms of breaking out of this idea of individuality
as being the source of identity as opposed to...
to community, right? So when we're talking about bringing life into the world, we're talking about
doing this in communal settings, right? So if you live by yourself, right, you could kind of do
that into your home for yourself, but also you're going to be involved in the parish community, right?
And so in the same way that I was saying masculinity can in part be worked out in
in providing, right?
this also is true on the other side for femininity. And I'm not only talking about feeding people,
but this does include feeding people, right? This does include sharing, you know, things you make
with your hands, whether that be food, whether that be other things, the work of your hand with
people. This includes mentoring young women, right? Serving as a spiritual mother in that way,
teaching.
skills, that same kind of thing, right? You can have just because you don't have the title mother
because you're not an avis, right? Doesn't mean you can't be a spiritual mother to other women.
And it certainly doesn't mean you can't be a spiritual daughter. And it certainly doesn't mean you
can't support the men who are in your life and your priest in the ministry in the
There are always trust me as a priest. There are always thousands of things that need to be done in a parish.
And two or three people who want to do them.
So there are all kinds of ways to contribute.
Right? And so this is something I said on Jonathan Peugeot's channel once. I think a lot of people misunderstood.
at least I hope they did because they called me a heretic.
But he asked whether cities have souls and I said yes,
and I think that's what freaked people out.
But the word soul, especially in Hebrew, just means life.
Right?
So each of us has life, right, within us, right?
But also communities, families and extended families.
So communities like parishes, right?
and communities like cities.
in this case have a shared life and that shared life is not just the sum of the parts of the
lives of the individual people. Right? And so on one hand, if we're talking about on the
masculine side, that life can either be in good order or not. Right? In the same way, that
can be an environment which is affirming the life that brings forth more life.
that encourages life, the abundant life that Christ was talking about, meaning the joy,
the love, the peace that comes from God, or communities could be very ugly. They could
become communities more characterized by death, right, and despondency rather than joy,
and bitterness, and hatred rather than love, right? And so part of being a spiritual mother
within a community is...
being the conduit through which that love and joy and peace and caring and life come into that community as a whole
Right, and there are lots of ways to do that that practical sharing element is a practical way to do that the mentoring
Organizing of things right of activities and of everything else
of everything else, all of those things are going to...
bring more life into the community and make it a place that is characterized by life and love and joy
right and
That's what you can play a part in doing right again. It doesn't have to be to a nuclear family
In fact the nuclear family we kind of have to get out of the way right it has to be bigger than that
That's too small. It has to be bigger than that right and so
Well, yes
You you kind of have to be married and probably have at least one kid to technically have a nuclear family
if we take nuclear...
family off the table, then that's not required for you to in the various levels of community
in which you live be someone who brings life and love and joy to each of those communities.
Yeah. So that gave you a few minutes. What you got, Father Andrew. Oh, okay. Oh, hey,
everybody. No, well, I mean, number one, that was lovely, Father. But the other thing I would,
I would add a little bit that I would...
ad is, you know, I think that especially if we, as we look at the way that God created
Adam and Eve and their particular emphases, right?
As Father Stephen said earlier in the show, they sort of major in one thing or another,
right?
That Adam, his job is mainly to do this work of subduing, which is like cultivating
and building, and that Eve's job is mainly to, you know, to be fruitful, to multiply, to
bring life, right?
I think that
that meditating on that. And again, it's because that these things serve the salvation of these people,
not because God is just assigning some kind of random task, you know. So within that then, I would also
add, especially that there's a really an internal aspect as well, right? Like I mentioned, you know,
this advice that I was given, get control of yourself. Now, the way that men and women get control
of themselves is different because that
our temptations tend to be different, right?
But I think that that's one of the best things
that can also be done is to stabilize oneself,
because we're all unstable in one way or another.
And whenever we feed our,
whenever we feed our temptations,
we become more unstable, right?
And so that would be the thing that I would add
is also to work on that internal life as well.
and think about the way that bringing
life into your own life, you know, how you can be focused on that rather than on death,
frankly, you know, the opposite, that that is a way to serve all the things that Father
was just talking about as well, you know, and to make sure that it's filled with prayer
and with devotion to God and, you know, all of that, right? And like I said, men and women
struggle towards that differently. I'm not a woman. I've never been a woman. I cannot
be a woman so
I don't know exactly what that is like.
I can only tell you what I've seen.
And it is different, that I do know,
that men and women simply struggle differently.
But one of the best ways I think to struggle well
is to find that experienced person
within your own parish family
or maybe a godmother or someone like that
who knows what they're doing and connect with them
and be mentored by them as well.
Right?
This is a fate that we pass from one person to the next and the way that we do it best is by the experienced person giving it to the less experienced person, right?
So so that's what I would add to all of that. Does that does that help you at all, Kavya?
That is enormously helpful. Thank you so much. Thank God. Well, thanks for calling this evening.
Absolutely. Thank you.
Alrighty. We uh we really need to uh
to push this nuclear family thing.
off the board. We can't make a lot of people mad with that.
I don't care. And we should say we're not trying to like, it's not about destroying the
nuclear family. No, it's it's conceptually, it's too small. Right. It's about not not idolizing
an isolating it. Right. So this is right. And this is and I understand why people are
so devoted to it, right? Because here's what's happened. Here's what's happened. What modern
is one of the many horrible things it's done to us.
Right is we are now in a situation where we are so alienated from everything and everyone
that the only refuge we have left is the nuclear family. Yeah. In our current society. Right. So
I understand why everybody's devoted to it and why I'd be talking about this. We'll get people
might get people mad, but understand what I'm saying. I'd not say we need to get rid of it and have
everyone just be this isolated, completely alienated person out of the world, right? The
The problem with having it as the last refuge though is that now here's how people feel.
I have two options.
I can either get into a nuclear family by finding someone to marry and trying to have a kid.
Or I'm going to be single.
Right.
I'm going to be alone.
And this is a huge issue.
I'm going to be isolated.
Those are the only two options, right?
And that's ridiculous.
Those have never been the only two options, right?
That's what we've been...
reduced to, right? And so we need to think bigger than that. No one is single. No one is, you feel
alienated and you've been alienated by everything in our society and our culture and our economy
and everything else, right? But that's not the way it should be and that shouldn't be what we're
doing as a church community. We should be reintegrating with each other and with God. That is the
the number one thing the church is doing. That's what the Eucharist is all about.
all about bringing us into communion and deeper communion with one another and with God.
Right. And I think this is one of the things that's so beautiful about monasticism. Is it simply
enacting that within the context of celibacy for that community? But I mean, if you look at the way
that an abbot functions or an abyss functions within their monastery and the way it is called a
brotherhood or a sisterhood for a reason. Like it's not just a word, you know. Like that's what happens
is it becomes...
a reconstitution of an extended family. And I think that's one of the reasons why
monasticism is valuable to us who are not monastics. It demonstrates how to do that as
a community who are not necessarily bound together with the ties of blood.
Right. And even in the church, everyone in the New Testament is called brethren. It's
not just brothers and sisters in Christ. That's not just a nice way of talking about each
other.
That
That should be real.
We are an extended kinship unit.
The other adults in your parish are your kids, aunts, and uncles.
Whether they're related to you by blood or not.
Right?
Big family.
Anyway, end of right.
It was a good rant though.
This is a beautiful, beautiful...
Yeah, but you know what's going to happen.
You know what's going to happen now?
Somewhere on Reddit, somewhere on Twitter, somebody's going to say, to young ones to destroy
the nuclear family.
I will read those.
post and laugh hardily. I enjoy being blamed.
Exercising the nuclear option.
Yes.
Right.
I mean, so okay, so one of the things that we see in the Old Testament, actually, some people
don't know this is in the Old Testament is this idea that Israel is supposed to be a
kingdom of priests. So I mean, does that like so? Okay, Exodus 19, five and six, right?
Now therefore if you will indeed obey my voice and keep my
covenant, you show being my treasured possession among all
peoples for all the earth is mine. And you show to be to me a
kingdom of priests and a holy nation. Doesn't that suggest that
Korah and sons were right? Hey, we're all holy here, right?
Yeah, I guess we got to rethink this whole thing. Oh,
yeah, the earth did swallow up in the suns. And the fire did go
out from the Lord and consume them. Yeah, it is good countermaning
evidence.
Yes. But this is, and we're going to see this in Act 3 when we eventually get there. Who knows when that'll be.
But it's very common in our time to pit the idea of everyone in the community exercising a kind of priesthood against the idea of there being particular people who are designated as priests.
Right? Very commonly those two ideas are seen as opposed to each other, but...
Here in Exodus, here in the Torah, they're not at all seen as opposed to each other.
Right?
They are both true.
So, how does that work?
Right?
If they are a kingdom of priests.
Well, we talked about those concentric circles in terms of the priesthood as it's laid out
in the Torah.
Right?
You have the high priest family.
You have the priestly clan as the circle around that.
You have the Levites as the circle around that.
Right?
And each of those groups is called
to a higher level of holiness. The high priest is familiar with the highest level of holiness.
The priests are called to the next highest level of holiness. Then the Levites. They are the
ones who are camped around the tabernacle. Then you go out to the other 11 tribes of Israel.
And what this is saying in Exodus 19 about them being a kingdom of priests and a holy nation
is that there's a
whole represent a priesthood in relation to who, right? So the high priest, the priest,
again, the Levites are a priesthood for the 11 tribes, right? The 12 tribes together,
Israel as a whole is a priesthood in relation to the 70 nations, right? And so this is why
we have so many commandments, especially in the holiness code. We've talked about X-15 on
on the show, right?
I never remember where I talk about it.
I think so, but it might be good to really focus on some of that.
We'll do it real briefly.
We have a lot of content still to go through.
This comes up in Acts 15, right?
But if you look at the holiness code in Leviticus,
which is roughly Leviticus 17 through 23, people kind of argue,
you know, hey, you got to publish journal articles
and write dissertation so people argue
about where it ends exactly, but something like 17 through 23 or 17 through 24.
It's referred to as the holiness code.
And in there, almost all of the commandments are directed to the people of Israel.
It says Moses, God says to Moses, tell the sons of Israel, no ham sandwiches, right?
Tell me something.
Right. Tell me something.
And then...
There are four commandments in there that are directed, he says, not only tell the sons of Israel,
but also all the foreigners who are in the land of Israel, who dwell in the land.
Even though they're not Israelites, they haven't been circumcised, they're not eating the Passover.
They still have to follow those four.
And those four are not at all coincidentally exactly the four things that in
and X-15 are prohibited.
Gentile Christians. Right? And so Axiophine is taking this very literal reading of Leviticus.
Almost like they think the law is still in effect. The Torah is still in effect. Go figure.
But the point here being for our purposes is that Israel is being held to a higher level of
holiness than the other nations are. Because they serve this priestly function over a
against the other nations.
And they are closer in.
They're in a closer concentric circle
around the place where God is dwelling.
And so they must have a higher level of holiness
than the Greeks, the Babylonians, the Egyptians
because they're Israel.
And so this is why we don't have commandments.
This is a difference between a lot of forms of Islam
and what we find in the Torah.
is that the Torah, they're never called.
you know, hey, go conquer Moab and make them stop eating pigs.
Right. And circumcise them all by force. Right. It's never,
this is the eternal law of God. You must get a subject the entire
world to it. It's explicitly the opposite. It's explicitly,
this is for you because you're this special people who with whom
God is dwelling, therefore you are now called to this higher level.
Right.
And it's directed to you.
And one primary place, this is just one example, but it's a really good example, where Israel
plays this function for the 70 nations, is at the Feast of Tabernacles as it's described
in Numbers 23.
We're all the Feast of Tabernacles.
Every day they give this set of offerings.
All the offerings each day are the same.
except for the number of bulls.
Yeah, yeah, if you read numbers 23,
starting from I think verse 12 or whatever it says,
and then offer this many bulls,
and then the next day then offer this many bulls.
And if you counted all up,
it turns out to be 70 bulls, total.
Right, one bull for each nation.
Right, so this is a place where they are making sacrifices
to Yahweh that got of Israel for the other nation.
right? They're interceding for
the world. The world, yeah, as a people together, as a community. So to move through this kind of
quickly, right, just to move us up to the time of Christ, right? Because some stuff happens between
Moses and the time of Christ. Meanwhile, things that 12 to 1500 years worth of stuff.
So what happens, this gets really messy.
during what's called the Hasmonian period, which is the period described in the books of
first and second Macabees, third Macabees is about Egypt, but first and second Macabees.
And our friend, Judas Macabius, aka Judah the Hammer.
The Hammer. Yes. I mean, living in a town called Amias, I really appreciate that.
Yes. Yes.
I don't think I
sent out my Hanukkah memes this year. Anyway, I really want to bring back as a
favor to the Jewish community, at least the English-speaking Jewish community
that's on the internet. I have these Hanukkah memes. I want to bring back an
awareness of Judah the Hammer. Right? There's too much about candles, too much
about gift giving. I want killing elephants and due to the hammerling.
to smack down on Greek people.
Yes.
Um,
black and Greek people, pagan Greek people.
It seems to be like every 13 year old Jewish kid in this country would agree with me that
that's way cooler.
I'm just guessing I'm not Jewish, but I bet I'm on board with this as well.
So, um, due to the hammer comes, right?
And he and his brothers, um, reestablish an independent Judea, right?
They have a revolution.
and they are reestablished independent Judea, they re-dedic-
the temple. That's what the Feast of Lights, what Hanukkah is all about. And then Judas
brother becomes the High Priest. Yep. Because why not? Yeah. Right. Yeah. So there's not some sort of
priestly descent, or he's not. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And so the Hasimonyans, they sort of
took the priesthood to the kingship and that it kind of gets worse because...
By the time you get to about 150 BC and John here canis, he makes himself both the king
and the high priest at the same time.
And sort of presents himself as a messianic figure, went and destroyed the Samaritan's temple
on Mount Gharism, which never got rebuilt.
Which just interesting fun point of fact, the rubble still existed at the time of Christ
That's what the Samaritan woman was referring to when she
She said this is where we worship.
Yeah.
They didn't help relations between Judaism and Samarit.
So, and then it's sort of then that family, the descendants of that family, who hold
the priesthood at the time of Christ.
This is the party that's called the Sadducees in the New Testament, who have control of the
temple in Jerusalem and its environs and the sacrifices.
is sort of an
sort of corruption of zetakites.
So they called themselves the zetakites
to act as if they were descended from zetak
because they could read.
And they saw that that's who the
high priests were supposed to be descended from.
Right.
But they were, they just identified as zetakites.
They were not actually zetakites.
And so they essentially, you know,
they're most famous for not believing
in the resurrection.
in the New Testament.
But we don't appreciate now the level of true corruption
that was there, where they had turned the temple
into essentially a business venture.
It was sort of Jerusalem temple ink.
And they did a deal with the Romans.
They did a deal with the Romans,
where they were allowed to collect the temple tax.
They were allowed to collect taxes from the people
to support and operate the temple.
And so what the
they would do is they would demand extortion at tax rates, and then when people couldn't
pay them, they would confiscate people's land to pay the debt.
And so by the time of Christ, about 70% of Judean land was owned by the Sadducees by the
high priestly family.
And the people, and then because they now essentially evicted people from the land that was given
them by the tor-
to their families, but given to them by God, they have basically evicted them. They would then
basically have them come back for slave wages as peasant farmers and work what used to be their
own land. Right. So basically the profit and the service with the profit from that going back also
to the Jerusalem temple.
So it's not just that people were selling...
had two expensive prices on their sacrifices when Jesus comes and cleanses the temple. There was a lot
more fiduciary irresponsibility going on at the Jerusalem temple by this point. And so this is what
lies behind a lot of the things that Christ directs toward the temple and the high priesthood in his
preaching. There's some really negative things that sound really uncrystallic to us that he says.
But this is why, right?
This is what they're literally oppressing the people, right?
They are supposed to shepherd these people,
and instead they're making lamb kabobs of these people, right?
Can you use a good Jubilee?
Yeah.
All right, well, that's the second half.
We're going to go ahead and take a short break
and we will be right back in a few minutes.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
We'll be back in a minute.
moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of
Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
New from Ancient Faith Publishing. God is a Man of War, the
problem of violence in the Old Testament, written and read by Stephen
the God who reveals himself in
Scripture may at times seem to conflict with what seems right to us.
But the ways of man lead to destruction, by so journeying through this tension, our
views of ourselves, our lives, God in his creation, are reshaped and reformed in a way
that is truly real.
Wrestling with Christ as he appears to us in the Bible, will yield his blessing only if
we allow ourselves to be molded and taught.
We cannot approach the Scriptures to find our own personal Jesus, who conforms to who
we may want or even demand that he be.
to Jesus probably does not.
exist and so will avail us nothing. Rather, we must come to know the only Jesus Christ who
does exist and through his grace offers to transform us into his likeness.
God is a man of war, the problem of violence and the Old Testament.
Now available as an audiobook at audible.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung. If you have a question call now at 855-237-23...
That's 855 AF radio.
You know, Father, I listening to that promo for your audio book, I never really realized
that there was that depeche mode reference in there before.
So your own personal Jesus, yeah.
So welcome back everybody.
So just a note, even though the voice of Steve just told everybody to call in, we're actually
not gonna take him or caused
tonight because we've got a little bit long and we still have some more to talk about.
So you'll just have to hold on to those for next time.
So were you just stunned at hearing the promo of your own voice, Father?
I evaded it mostly.
Oh, wait, no, it's one of those.
Get out.
Yeah.
Run.
Fly.
Yeah.
Yeah, um, right, right.
So, okay, so we're continuing to talk about the priesthood as the third half of the show,
and where we left it off was with the super oppressive situation of the Sadducees
and the time of Christ who controlled the temple and had set themselves up as being the
priestly cast as it were at that point.
So what happens then with the coming of Christ?
I mean, he comes in and puts the smack down, you know, there in the temple.
chords, but there's way more actually going on in terms of Christ and the priest did it, right?
Right, right. And so, I mean, this even gets back, we talked about this a little in our Melchizedek
episode, but this even gets back into the sort of messianic expectation that we find playing out
in the second temple period, right? And so, there are a couple of options. There are sources where
where there seem to be two messiahs.
sort of a priestly Messiah and a kingly Messiah,
where these things are still separate.
But often what we see is that as with Melchizedek,
and this is particularly as we talked about in that episode
under the influence of Psalm 110 or Psalm 109,
where the Lord Messiah is sort of combined
with the priesthood of Melchizedek, right?
We see that the idea was that the Messiah was
going to bring these things back together, was going to bring the high priesthood and kingship
back together and reunite them. And this is related to the whole idea of Christ as the second Adam
that's going to play out in St. Paul's epistles and other places. We remember Adam is priest and
King. We saw the high priest.
is presented again as sort of this new atom within the paradise of the Tabernacle or the temple,
and then now also, right, the idea is that that is that being restored represents a restoration
of humanity, a restoration of human nature. All of these ideas are sort of intertwined in what is
expected from the Messiah. And so as you can read it,
lengthen Hebrews.
Christ is the high priest, Sin Quanon, because he is the ultimate fulfillment in the sense of filling
to overflowing the role of priesthood. So he represents God to man in that he is the express
image of the Father. Right. Right. He is God. Right. And he represents man to God.
because he is truly and fully human. Right. Right. And our human nature is united to God
in his person. Right. And so this makes him based on the definition of a priest. This makes him the
the the great high priest. Right. Right. Right. This is. I mean, in a sense, a priest to be a true priest
is to be Christ.
That's what priesthood is aiming at, is aiming at being Christ.
Right.
And so we see that in the church, this Christ as high priest imagery surrounds the bishop.
The icon of Christ, the great high priest, is on the bishop's throne.
and his vestments match what Christ is wearing in that, right?
and are roughly parallel to the high priest of the Old Testament. But the idea here is that
because we now have the fulfillment of this in Christ, the bishop now, the person who has the
roughly equivalent role of the high priest and the Old Covenant is now the icon of Christ.
Right? Is the icon of Christ in our in our midst. Right?
And so this reunion...
doesn't stop with Christ reuniting the priesthood that was split in Moses and Aaron.
Right. Between kingship and priesthood. Right. But it continues. Right. It continues all the way
down because Christ doesn't just restore some offices or some roles or some particular historical
persons. He restores humanity. Right. Right. With what was created to be by God from the beginning.
And so this has
a chain reaction, right? And so this also reunites priest and elder of the people, right?
The two words, right, in Greek, the areas from the old, let's use the Old Testament for
priests and Presbyterra, Presbyteros, that's used of the elders of the people, right? Who
of the people, right, who had the priesthood taken away at the golden calf.
right now that has been reunited for them as well.
Right, right.
And so the prespiter, right, in the new covenant now
has this priestly iconic function.
And that's why prized and prespiter are related.
Right, English.
Yeah, okay, yes.
Two father Andrew.
Thank you very much for that.
for that.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, so I mean, okay, again, little disclaimer, etymology is not what determines
meaning, but it can tell us a lot about how words have been used in the past. So priest and
presbyter in English are both descended from the Greek Puresviteros and what they represent in terms
of the etymology is that English borrowed the same word at two different points and it's
history. The first time we get it, so the so priests comes, you know, in Old
English it's preost. And that actually comes from having borrowed that word from
Greek through Latin into Old Germanic. And then it makes its way into Old
English and into modern English. So that's where we get preost and then priest,
which then gets commonly used to refer to both Christian priests and also pagan
priest, right? But by the time it gets used in old English,
It's being used to refer to Christian priests, right?
That's just the way it's used.
And then later, the same word gets borrowed again,
but more directly in, I think via French maybe
because of those Normans.
Man, Normans.
But then it comes in as presbyter.
So it sounds a little bit more obviously from presvideros,
right, presbyteris or some,
or I'm not sure how to pronounce it in Latin.
And then that gets used very exclusively to refer to Christian clergy.
So the fun thing is, now, I mean, most languages don't have this, right?
But English, what's fun about English is it often does borrow the same word at multiple times in history.
And then we get different forms of it.
So the fun thing about the way that English has those two words, Presbyter and Priest,
is that it just shows the union, the union, you know,
as you said, the reunion of...
a priesthood to eldership, it just sort of illustrates it because of this linguistic history.
So understood correctly, they really are synonyms.
Right?
Now we do tend to use the modern English word priest to translate that Greek word EFs
and then presbyter is which is basically an almost a transliteration of presbyteros.
And that's okay.
But we should at least know that they both ultimately come from that way.
where it put us be to the Rose is where it kind of comes in English. So it's just one of the fun things about the history of English that illustrates this point about priesthood being restored to Presbyterry, so to speak by Christ, you know, that priesthood comes back into eldership.
So that's what an elder is within the Church, is they are appreased by virtue of this.
So that's your, well I'm not going to say that's your own yet, an apology lesson for today, everybody, but that's, that's what,
of your etymology lessons for today. So yeah, it's just I don't know. It's a cool feature of English.
It just illustrates this really beautifully. We need to make Father Andrew's etymology corner
like feature to be like theme music. Yeah, a little bit of music at the beginning.
Etymology. So I'll think about a title for that. That'd be good. Yes. So angles on etymology. Anyway.
So
That's a very good pun, by the way, that's good.
Thank you.
Non-ungly said, um, jelly.
The, um, and so we also see play out, right?
We see this play out in the book of Acts, right?
That there's also this need, right, for, uh, in the, in the New Testament priesthood, right?
There's a lot of work to be done, right?
There are a lot of support functions in the same way they were with the Levites in the old covenant,
supporting the
priesthood. And so we see deacons show up in the book of Acts and then they get talked
about later in St. Paul's pastoral epistles. And this becomes sort of a catch-all category
for a whole bunch of offices in the early church when you look at the early church orders
from the late first and early second centuries of deacons and deacons and subdeacons and
doorkeepers and exorcists.
Yeah, cause the iconos just means.
servant, right? Yeah, in a broad, in a broad, broad sense. And it's interesting, like
that sense of Deakin being a kind of catch all that refers to multiple different roles.
It still exists, like in the coptic churches and the Syriac churches and those influenced
by them. I've heard them refer to reader deacons and subdeacons and, you know, and then
they'll use the phrase full deakin to refer to what is generally in English, in any way,
is called a deacon. Although like in in in Arab
you've got Shamas al-Nur, which means Deacon of the Light, which is a subdeacon,
and then you've got Shamas al-Njil, which is the Deacon of the Gospel, which is
the role that we normally call a Deacon in English. So it's interesting
and it has that broad, broad sense, very much like the Levites, had all these
different kinds of roles, and that's a lot of people. I mean, the Levites are not
just a group of men. It's all of them in their families. It's a whole tribe,
or the liver.
It's a whole Mishpaka. Oh, I don't know. It's a Yiddish pronunciation of a Hebrew word.
Okay. But so, and just to save everybody a PS on the angry letter you're writing about me
blowing up the nuclear family, because since I said the word deaconess, right? Yes, deaconess
is in the early church, were not women who were made deaconess. Deaconess was its own
thing. It's a separate thing.
Yeah, it's its own thing that men could not do
It was its own thing and that it but that is that is parallel what you think about because the Levites when we're talking about the Levites
We're not just talking about the male Levites right there were female Levites including a group of women who dwelt at the gates of the tabernacle
right who
did things like sewing and mending
investments and parts of the tabernacle and assistance.
with all kinds of things. So there were female assistants who had their own duties in the old
covenant, and that continues in the new covenant. There's this continuity. But so we have these structures
that emerge within the New Testament that are parallel to the similar structures in the old
covenant, right? But then have found their fulfillment now in crime.
right and sort of like how they were concentric circles, there are also concentric circles in a sense
now, because every bishop is also a priest, and also a deacon. So if you have bishop as the center
circle, then the circle around that would be the press bitter it, and then the circle around that
would be the deaconate. Right. And then you could put another circle with sort of the sub-deaconate,
write all those other offices, right? And then...
in the circle outside that, the people, right?
Because just as the people of Israel
as a whole exercise to certain kind of priesthood
in the old covenant,
so also in exactly the same way,
using exactly the same words,
for example, in first Peter, two verse nine,
the members of the Christian community,
the members of the church is a whole exercise
a kind of, the exact same kind of priesthood.
Yeah, I mean, same p-
pretty much almost exactly quotes this from the Old Testament. A chosen race, a royal priest,
that a holy nation, yeah, and it's interesting, it has this purpose. That you may proclaim the
excellencies of him who called you out of darkness into his marvelous light. Like the whole point
of being that the church is this royal priesthood, this holy nation, is so that they can
you know, bring God to the world and bring the world to God. I mean, it's exactly the same thing.
Exactly the same thing
sorry, dispensationalists.
So this means that the church has the same relationship to the world that Israel had to the
70 nations, right?
That our task is to represent God to the world and the world to God, that our goal is to
integrate, right?
If the church is the new paradise, right, then we're going out and like Adam integrating,
conquering.
Right, right, not imposing our will right. It's dominating right bring people into paradise and they become conformed to paradise not
like
You know, this is sort of utopian totalitarianism. I mean, that's the most extreme version. Okay. Yeah, but not like you know
Go out and make everybody behave a certain way right or like live you said about Rome
Create a wasteland and call it peace. It's really peaceful out there now that all the people are dead
Yeah, um, right.
And then also on the other side, interceding for the world before God.
And this is why the Eucharist is offered for the life of the world and for its salvation.
Right. Right. Right.
According to the liturgy of St. Basil.
So this priesthood of the faithful,
right, within the church, just like in Israel, is not opposed to
there being certain people who exercise another kind of priesthood.
These aren't opposed ideas, right?
Priesthood is always exercised in relation to God and then someone or something else, right?
So the bishops are exercising a priesthood to all of the circles outside of them.
So they are, bishops are priests, two priests.
They are priests to deacons. They are priests to the faithful and they are priests to the world.
Presbyters are priests to the deacons to the faithful and to the world.
And then they'll tell two friends and then we'll tell two friends.
And so on and so on. Right.
So you get to the people, the laity, the faithful are priests to the outside world of the church.
Right. And we see the sort of fulfillment of this that in the book of Revelation actually over and over again. Yeah, repeatedly. Okay. Revelation 1 6
God and made us a kingdom priests to his God and father to him be glory and demean forever and ever. Amen
510 and you have made them a kingdom and priests to our God and they shall reign on the earth and
And then 20 verse six, bless and holy is the one who shares in the first
resurrection over such the second death.
has no power, but they will be priests of God and of Christ and they will reign with him for a
thousand years. So you've got that priesthood and kingship kingdom and priests, priestly kingdom,
you know, like it's just over and over again. That's that's the way that the image of what it is,
the fulfillment of the kingdom of God in this world looks like according to the book of Revelation.
Right. So now that we've laid all that out, Protestant friends, Polo Pichere.
Let's have a talk.
We love you.
Yes.
We're not here to dominate you or argue with you.
We want to integrate you into the church.
But, um, that's, um, yeah, let's talk.
So, and the reason we're doing this,
this is not an apologetic show.
Right. Right.
But the reason we're addressing this in this way
with our Protestant friends is because we actually get this question a lot.
a lot.
Right.
We do.
Father Andrew reads every email we get, I skim some of them, but I've noticed in that skim
that we get this question a lot, right, about priesthood in the New Covenant, about New
Testament priesthood, about why there are priests in the Orthodox Church, right?
And we're talking about this with our Protestant friends because our Roman Catholic friends
have priests too, so they don't need to have this talk.
Right.
Generally this idea that exists that
the priesthood of the Old Testament gets set aside by Christ.
That all of it is sort of like his anti-Sadjussi language
and actions and stuff, and they're tearing down
of the temple, that that equals end of the priesthood.
We don't need that anymore.
It's over now, right?
So, and then they'll often say, well, Christ fulfilled it,
which means within this vision that it's over,
that it's a ball.
You know, that fulfillment means abolition.
Right, which is, I mean, this is a fit, right?
Yes, Christ said he didn't come to abolish the law.
He came to fulfill it, right?
But that doesn't mean that we just chuck the law
and then when someone accuses us of abolishing it,
we say, no, it's not abolished, it's fulfilled.
Yeah.
If it's still sitting in the dumpster, it's abolished.
It doesn't matter what you call it.
Okay, it doesn't matter whether you get fired from your job,
terminated or released from your contract,
you're still unemployed, right?
Go.
Yes.
So yeah, fulfillment is to fill it up to the full in overflowing.
Right.
It's the opposite of abolishing it.
Yeah.
It's.
That's why Christ makes that distinction.
Right.
So the priesthood of the new covenant is not less than the priesthood
of the old covenant.
Right.
more than
more than the priesthood of the old covenant, right? That's what we should expect, expect
to see. And if you tried to apply that kind of argument consistently, right, it would have
some really bad results. Yeah, for instance, the phrase, two fulfill all righteousness.
I don't have to worry about righteousness anymore. Yeah, it's been fulfilled. Right.
Right. Christ will fill all the commandments of the law. So I don't have to worry about any of
of them now, right?
We would never...
say that. No one would ever say that. Our Protestant friends would not say that, right?
But so you shouldn't say it selectively about certain parts of the Torah then either. Right.
So if but if you're going to take that approach, right, that rather than
then eldership and priesthood coming back together,
that eldership remains but priesthood is gone. Right? Either it's done...
with or I don't know Christ brought it to heaven. He's still the high priest but
there are no other priests. Some version of that where they're not
integrated right they're not reintegrated. Then there are some questions you
have to answer like why do the structures that like St. Paul lays out in the past
moral epistles are the structures that we see emerge in the book of Acts. The
structures we see emerge in the first century church.
Why are those directly parallel to so clearly as we've seen so directly parallel to the old testament structures?
And yeah, and in some cases using the exact same words
Right
Right why are that if this is a new thing if the old thing is gone and this is a whole new thing
Why does the new thing look so much like the old thing?
might it not be that
Our point that the new thing is the fulfillment the filling up of the old thing
might that not be a better way to end?
interpret that. But this also causes a bunch of problems down the chain. Right? Because what happens is
what happens when we talk about the offices in the church then as they're usually talked about in like the the Protestant Reformers and
most of them take some kind of three office view, meaning they have something similar at the Protestant Reformers. I mean you have
something like
a bishop or a pastor, you have something like elders, right? And you have something like
deacons, right? Sometimes the names are a little different depending on who you're reading.
As you go forward in Protestantism, that's not always true. You get various two office
things where sometimes you'll have a pastor in deacons and a lot of American evangelical
churches, especially Baptist churches. You'll get in, you get two office Presbyterians
where they just have prespitors and deacons.
but they have two kinds of prespitors and one of those kinds of prespitors looks a lot like a bishop.
But you get what I mean. So it sort of plays out in different ways. But the basis for that,
the whole basis for that then, if you set the Old Testament aside, if the Old Testament thing,
everything with the priesthood and the Old Testament is now irrelevant, right? Then your only
basis for that are the words of St. Paul and the pastoral epistles. Right. So you get Paul
Timothy, it's time.
creating these roles. Right. Yeah. Right. And you could say by fiat apparently just saying this is what I'm
excited. Either by fiat or right, you know, to be fair, right. It's scripture. So God speaking through
St. Paul says this is how he wants the church to be organized, but it's just a command. Right.
Either issued by St. Paul on behalf of God or by God through St. Paul, however you want to see that,
Right but so it's just this command okay.
And it's not based on anything in particular.
It's divine command, right?
So if they're not connected like that, right,
then they become subject to a whole lot of interpretation.
And first and second Timothy and Titus aren't that long.
And they're not that detailed.
Right.
There's not a lot there about the rules.
So, for example, when...
St. Paul says that a prespitor must be literally says a one woman man
Is he just translated husband of one wife?
Right
So does that mean does that mean you just you can't be a polygamist?
Does that mean he can't be divorced?
Is the male part the important part?
Or is just the only married once the important part and it could be a woman?
Right
Right? And this is not...
just me making up hypotheticals. Yeah, this is this is real applied stuff. This is real
life, right? Among our Protestant friends in their various communities, right? These are
arguments that are made, right? Because all we have to go on are these few words from St.
Paul, right? And so how do we interpret? How do we understand them? What are the parts
that he's meaning to be a rule and what are the parts that are not really rules and just
descriptive, right? And so that then, once you can read.
these lots of different ways and make lots of different arguments, right? You get a kind
of chaos that you see play out in church leadership in various different types of churches,
whether they're in a denomination or not a domination or what have you, right? And
so it's not just a question of women's ordination, right? That obviously enters into this, as
we just said, but...
Now, we've disconnected. This is a new role. This is not related to priesthood.
Right? So other than the qualifications that St. Paul gives, we also aren't given a whole lot
of detail on how they are to function. St. Paul tells us the kind of person who should be made
one, even that subject to interpretation. But once we have this person in this office, in this
role, what do they do and how do they do it? Well, we can't go back to the priesthood stuff,
because they are.
priests, right? And so this gets tends to be, right? This becomes an ideological superstructure
thing that gets molded by outside forces of the society.
Yeah, right. So it gets interpreted often along the contours of being about power, right?
So there's this kind of Marxist social interpretation that's put upon it.
capitalist. Yeah, yeah. Yeah, exactly. Yeah, exactly. It becomes about controlling people
and that sort of thing. Yeah, who controls the money, who controls the organization, who controls,
right? So you get the pastor is a CEO and then he has a board that's like the board of a corporation.
Right. Yeah. Who gets to tell people what you have to believe? Like it becomes about handing down
on edicts from on high.
You know.
I.
And it's funny, like it, it, it, again, it begins to resemble this paganized view of the priesthood.
Right.
You know, where, where it gets the, again, the conduit gets stopped up.
Because Christ told us, right, explicitly, the Lord's the nations, the Lord's the Gentiles,
the Lord's the 70 nations that they lord it over people.
So should it not be with you?
Right.
So there was supposed to be this sort of counterpoint between how priesthood functions
in the church and how leadership functions in external organizations in the world.
But the exact opposite has happened.
So we get this CEO thing, we get this power dynamic, right?
I'm the boss, right?
I'm the leader, I'm the one in charge.
Or you get the opposite, right?
You get the opposite where especially more recently, 1970s and on in the United States,
example where it becomes all about the the pastor
is and the elders are they are there to provide care of a certain sort right they are they are caregivers
to provide pastoral and spiritual care they're there to nurture people spiritually right and this
again when you define the role of the church leadership in that way what do you think's going to
happen well I know a lot of women who are really gifted at care professions right and they're going to
Look.
at these church leadership positions from which they were traditionally excluded in their
minds, right? Because again, this is just a role that St. Paul delivers the first word on,
and he's been interpreted historically in Protestant Communions to be only talking about men,
right? So they turn to, I'm excluded for this, but I seem to be really gifted in this.
Hmm.
And so they say, well, why am I so gifted in this, if I'm not supposed to do...
it, that is it makes sense. Right. And they interpret that as God calling them to do it. Right.
They interpret it that way because we've redefined the it. We've redefined what it is. Right.
As as this function. And so why should someone of any gender or any age or any marital status? Right.
be able to do that if they're gifted to do it.
Right. And so you get both, right? This dynamic is why you have both like liberalizing trends
within Protestant churches and authoritarian trends in other Protestant churches, right?
Where you have pastors dictator on the one hand and pastors carrying nurture on the other,
Right?
And so if the presbyter isn't a priest, right?
if the pastor isn't a priest, then he, she, they can end up being, right, you know, a counselor,
a motivational speaker, a CEO, a worship leader, or a liturgist, right? All of those things become
the definition because there isn't another real biblical one. And so we get one from the culture.
Yeah, and, you know, it's not that the
most of those things are bad in and of themselves.
Right?
It's, you know, a counselor is a good thing to have,
you know, like it's good to have a counselor, right?
But that's not what priesthood is.
And as we've seen, it's not,
therefore what Presbyterat is.
Yeah.
Like a Presbyter might be a counselor.
Like there are, I know some priests who are,
you know, like they actually have that ability
and training and they're good at it.
But...
You know, that's not that's not core. That's not within the core of what the priest had actually
Yes, they're that qua person not qua priest. Yeah. Yeah, and to be fair to be fair right this
same pressure that has been exerted on our Protestant friends has also exerted at least in this
country and I'm sure in other Western countries on the Orthodox Church. Yeah, there's the expectation
Orthodox clergy are supposed to be these things too. Yeah, are supposed to be you know master
You
liturgists or CEO of a small and nonprofit or or or what have you, right? So this is this is a
Affleck's it but but here's what I'm saying to my Protestant friends. Honestly, the way out of that
mess is and and our Protestant friendship have no problem with this is to go back into the scriptures
and recover the connection between the offices of leadership.
in the new covenant, in the New Testament, and those in the Old Covenant and the Old Testament,
and to see that presbyters are now once again priests. And then priesthood is how authorities
to be exercised in the Church in this transparent way. Well, to wrap things up, you know, one of the
things that occurred to me as we were having our conversations about all this is
I mean, it's no secret. My great love for the works of J.R. R. Tolkien. One of the, his
very good and remarkable essays is called On Ferry Stories. And it's a piece of literary
criticism. It's a lecture that he gave and then got published some years later. And he
makes the point, so just hang with me here. He makes the point that a fairy story or a fairy
detail is not a story about...
fairies, right? You know, however you want to define fairies, he actually hated the idea of fairies as being you know
diminutive little people. For him, they were otherworldly almost humans, but you know elves or whatever.
But he makes the point that a fairy story or a fairy tale is actually about human beings
entering into a realm called that he would call fairy, which he didn't invent that term.
and it's often spelled F-A-E-R-I-E.
and that it both encompasses the idea of human beings crossing into another realm
and also standing in the presence of something otherworldly.
That's how he defines what a fairy story or fairy tale is about.
And of course, if you're familiar with his fictional works,
you know that that is a pretty significant element in what he likes to write about.
and um
You know as we try to get our minds around as much as possible what the priesthood is
Which is not totally possible because this is this is a gift from God and and it's about participating in who Christ is
So we can't really truly
truly understand it or comprehend it
We can participate in it
But as we try you know to understand on some level so that we can participate well
Well, this was one of the things that occurred to me about what...
priesthood is, not just in terms of like being a presbyter, like Father Steven and I are,
but in terms of what it means to be in the people of God, right? So on the one hand, we come
in contact with what is otherworldly, right? And I don't just mean the unseen world in general,
I mean God in particular.
That art
task is to encounter him, right? But also our task, you know, especially as a holy nation,
as a royal priesthood together, a kingdom of priests is to bring the world into contact
with God. So we represent God to the world and we present the world to God, right? This
is that basic dynamic of the conduit that we've been talking about in this whole episode.
I think that one
of the ways that we can do that is especially by trying as we do on this podcast to look at
and to understand what the scriptures say about God's presence and work in the world and his
holy ones that are working alongside him. Right? So it's a priestly act, for instance, to tell someone
the story of a saints life because you're doing that. You're becoming that conduit.
right and then it's a priestly act to help someone become.
like Christ, you know, you're being the conduit in the other direction. You're presenting them to
God, right? So, you know, ultimately it's not about fairy tales, right? But fairy tales are one way
of trying to understand that encounter between the human and the other worldly, the human and the
divine, right? And I think that that's part of the value of reading stories like that,
that under staining stories like
that is that it helps to shape and to nurture the imagination so that when we encounter
these things in Scripture, it makes a little bit more sense to us because we've already encountered
it in some way in something that's a little bit more bite-sized. You know, they're not absolutely
analogous. It's not absolutely analogous, but it can help to form the human person
to be more receptive to the reality that is being described in Scripture.
And to be more receptive to the reality that we actually encounter in the divine services,
especially the divine liturgy itself, the Eucharist, right?
And so, like I said, it's not the only angle, it's not required, but it's one angle.
And I think that all of us as human beings encounter stories, which are about this encounter
again of the human with the other world with the
divine with the astonishing. And I believe that the more that we become the story tellers
that God has made us to be, and by that, I don't mean that you necessarily have to write
novels or whatever, but simply to tell the story of the scriptures, to tell the story of
the lives of the saints, then we are functioning in that priestly way, one way of functioning
in that priestly way. There's a lot of ways. But
but this is one in particular. Father Stephen?
I didn't know you liked Tolkien. I do. Oh, okay. Now I've been
hiding it for a while. Even for all these years I learned
something about you. Yep. Um, so as we talked about, uh,
priesthood is a way of relating to the world and the people
in it and relating to God.
We've fallen into all kinds of different ways of relating to other people and relating
to God that are not what we've described tonight as priesthood.
But let's think about for a minute what that might look like if we decided to do that.
What does it look like if someone who's parenting children, parents them?
in a priestly manner. Well, for one thing, then a child being disobedient wouldn't be about them
transgressing or challenging your authority. It wouldn't be about your ego versus their ego,
and your ego needing to crush theirs and put them back in their place as a child under your authority.
It might look a lot more like seeing a child's disobedience as them having a
and alienated themselves from God and from the family.
And your task is a parent being to do the work with them,
to reintegrate them, to bring them back into communion
with the family and with God.
It's a very different thing.
And the same thing could be true with employees,
with students who you teach, with people who use supervised
in a job situation.
We can approach other people in the sense of wanting to reintegrate what is broken, to reconnect what's been separated,
to rebuild after all the alienation we've all suffered, reconnect into heal.
We all have the capacity to do that in every encounter we have.
And that's not just true on this personal basis, right?
Right because the Christian world, especially in the United States.
I'm sure this is true other places too.
This means a whole lot of its energy.
Trying to enforce the rules that govern the lives of Christians on the country around us
and the world around us.
We approach our larger community, not now our church community, not now our parish community,
but our city, our state, the country we live in.
as a place
that we need to now use power relationships, use what power we have as citizens to try
to conform it, to try to sort of conquer it, to try to take control of it, and then make
it into what it should be. And this is not just true of one quote on quote side. I don't
know that there are even two sides in American politics anymore, but that's a whole other
topic. But you know on one side right we
need to seize the levers of power and remake things and use our power to make
sure that certain sins are made illegal so that we can try to stomp them out.
Even among people who don't know Christ and don't believe in Christ will cross a
couple sins off the list that we won't let them commit. The other side says we
need to do something by force using the mechanisms of power.
using our power as citizens to make sure that the people who we should be feeding get fed by the state,
the people who we should be clothed and get clothed by the state. Right.
And both sides are not approaching the world as if they, as Christians, are priests for the world.
Because I as a priest, am not called to go run for mayor.
In fact, I'm not allowed to, as an Orthodox priest, or Congress, or President.
I'm not called to take over those mechanisms and try to enforce these things.
I'm called upon as a priest to represent Christ to the world and the world to Christ.
God didn't send us into the world to condemn it.
Whether that's condemning it.
as a woke scold or condemning it as a Puritan of the more traditional type, right, but that
the world might be saved. That's why we're sent. And so we need to be going out into the
world and seeking to integrate the world into the church as the new paradise on this larger
scale and that's a priestly function that
as we said, every single Christian has. And we do it directly through direct action with people.
We bring Christ to them and then we bring them back to Christ. At first that may only be in prayer,
maybe eventually we get them to come to Christ themselves. But that has to always be our goal.
Because Lord willing, if that's how we're living our life as Christians.
Then as those people become Christians, guess what?
They're going to live a Christian morality.
And they're going to care for the poor and the needy.
They're going to do all of those things that we've been busy trying to do politically
and by the way failing miserably.
They're going to do all those things as Christians.
And better than that, they're going to find salvation and eternal life,
which is a whole lot.
more important than the wealth gap or how much sin is going on in any given city. So those
are my thoughts. Amen. Well, that is our show for today. Thank you very much, everyone,
for listening. If you didn't get a chance to call in during the live broadcast, we'd
love to hear from you either via email at Lord of Spirits at ancient faith.com or you
can message us at our Lord of Spirits podcast Facebook page.
I
everything, fathers to even skims everything, but we can respond to everything. And we do
save what you said for possible use in future episodes. I skimmed some things. Join us for
our live broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7pm Eastern 4pm Pacific.
And if you're on Facebook, you can like our page, join our discussion group, leave reviews
and ratings everywhere, but please share this show with a friend whom you know is going to love it.
and you know, don't be on Facebook if you don't have to.
And finally, be sure.
to go to ancientfaith.com, stroke support, and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you very much.
Good night and may God bless you all.
You've been listening to The Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Fox.
to young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne
and the beasts and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000
than thousands of thousands, saying with a loud voice,
worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and
strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11
11-12.
Welcome to Tending the Garden of Our Hearts.
I'm Alisa Bielatech, and I'm Christina Wenger.
We're here with another meditation for the whole family.